<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title> - Info</title>
    <link href="https://grantspassoregon.github.io/tags/info/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://grantspassoregon.github.io"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2023-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://grantspassoregon.github.io/tags/info/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Web Viewer Links</title>
        <published>2023-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://grantspassoregon.github.io/newsfeed/web-viewer-links/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://grantspassoregon.github.io/newsfeed/web-viewer-links/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A commonly-requested feature for the City Web Viewer is access to public documents, such as final plats or financial agreements, including Fee in Lieu, Deferred Development, Service &amp;amp; Annexation Agreements or Advance Finance Districts.  We are pleased to announce that the new version of the Web Viewer map includes web links to these various public documents, making them accessible to view and download for members of the public.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access final plats, turn on the visibility of the Subdivision Plats layer in the Property category of the Layers widget.  When you click on a feature, the viewing link will appear in the pop-up menu:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt; Figure 1.  Web Link for Final Plats.&lt;&#x2F;caption&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;

&lt;img src=&#x2F;content&#x2F;newsfeed&#x2F;web_links_plats.png alt=&quot;Web Links for Final Plats&quot; width=300&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;center&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;img src=&#x2F;content&#x2F;newsfeed&#x2F;web_links_plats.png alt=&quot;Web Links for Final Plats&quot; width=300&gt; --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access City financial agreements, turn on the appropriate layer in the Planning category under Agreements and Financial sub-heading.  When you click on a feature, the viewing link will appear in the pop-up menu:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt; Figure 2.  Web Link for AFDs.&lt;&#x2F;caption&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;

&lt;img src=&#x2F;content&#x2F;newsfeed&#x2F;web_links_afd.png alt=&quot;Web Links for AFDs&quot; width=300&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;center&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preparing this service for public access was a non-trivial process, because the City computer network was not set up to support this functionality.  Staff at the City access work documents using a shared network drive.  Our GIS layers often include links to documents on our network drive, and in ArcGIS these links will open the document on a PC that is operating on our internal network.  In the past, when the public wanted access to these documents, they would drop by the planning counter in person, or contact a member of our staff by email or phone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To facilitate public viewing and download, staff migrated storage of these documents to the City website, adding web links to over 4,000 features on the Web Viewer map.  If you discover a link that fails to open, or desire access to an additional class of documents, please let us know at &lt;a href=&quot;emailto:gis@grantspassoregon.gov&quot;&gt;gis@grantspassoregon.gov&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Beta Testing for New Web Viewer</title>
        <published>2023-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://grantspassoregon.github.io/newsfeed/beta-web-viewer/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://grantspassoregon.github.io/newsfeed/beta-web-viewer/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;beta-web-viewer-open-for-testing&quot;&gt;Beta Web Viewer Open For Testing&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since releasing the Web Viewer in February of 2022, we have received a lot of welcome feedback on how we can improve the user experience.  Although some of the comments have been directed toward how we could improve organization and layout of the map data, the majority of feedback has been about issues with the application interface.  Some commonly-desired features include:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A button to &amp;quot;restore your previous session&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filters for selecting types of content within features.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A directional navigation widget.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools for selecting multiple features and viewing their attributes in a table.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better drawing and measurement tools.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we can upgrade the existing Web Viewer to a new version, we need to field test the new app and make sure that it works as intended.  This is where you come in!  Help us test the new Beta version today by clicking on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;experience.arcgis.com&#x2F;experience&#x2F;9c1a9de28a864f59a6fcd5d4dbb5f00c&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why does the Beta version looks so different?&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; The current Web Viewer uses an ArcGIS Instant App template to provide an application framework.  Instant App templates include a thematic layout and a number of optional app features by default.  Because they are quick and easy to set up, an Instant App template made sense when were starting out, to get a product out quickly and start delivering services to our users right away.  However, these app templates are limited in their ability to incorporate new features and tools.  In order to get the customizability that we needed, we needed to go beyond Instant Apps and target a richer application framework.  Previously, the standard tool for building web apps in ArcGIS was the App Builder.  In recent years, the App Builder has been deprecated in favor of the new Experience Builder.  Experience Builder is based upon the latest version of Java, and is capable of integrating 2D and 3D map layouts, among other improvements.  Eventually, we may decide to start building custom widgets for our apps, in which case we can use Experience Builder Developer Edition or the JavaScript SDK for ArcGIS to create a fully-custom web app.  Custom apps are more difficult to host and maintain, so for this Beta version we are using Experience Builder.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Features that are not implemented in the Beta version, but are on the roadmap to be implemented in the future:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web links to public records (Fee in Lieu, Service &amp;amp; Annexation and Deferred Development agreements, AFDs)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved content organization of layers in the map.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is your preferred feature not on the list?  Do you have changes you would like to see in the next Beta version?  Let us know!  Email us at gis@grantspassoregon.gov.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
